<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Italian prophecier. That is, A prognostication made for the yeere of our Lord God 1622. Practised by Antonio Magino, Professour of the Mathematickes, in the towne of Bononia, written fiue yeeres past: declaring many wonders and fearefull proceedings, wherewith the world is threatned to happen therein by warre this present yeere. With notable complaints made by diuers nations, touching the present estate of their countrey. Faithfully translated out of Italian into Dutch, and now into English</title>
            <author>Magini, Giovanni Antonio, 1555-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103998</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839739</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 850:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Italian prophecier. That is, A prognostication made for the yeere of our Lord God 1622. Practised by Antonio Magino, Professour of the Mathematickes, in the towne of Bononia, written fiue yeeres past: declaring many wonders and fearefull proceedings, wherewith the world is threatned to happen therein by warre this present yeere. With notable complaints made by diuers nations, touching the present estate of their countrey. Faithfully translated out of Italian into Dutch, and now into English</title>
                  <author>Magini, Giovanni Antonio, 1555-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages cropped at foot, with some loss of signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Italian Prophecier.</p>
            <p>THAT IS, A PROGNOSTICATION MADE FOR THE YEERE OF OVR LORD GOD 1622.</p>
            <p>Practiſed by <hi>Antonio Magino,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of the Mathematickes, in the Towne of BONONIA, written fiue yeeres paſt: declaring many wonders and fearefull proceedings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the world is threatned to happen therein by Warre this preſent yeere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With notable complaints made by diuers</hi> Nations, touching the preſent eſtate of their Countrey.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated out of Italian into Dutch, and now into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Printed MDCXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4187:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is well knowne to all men of great account, and Mathematicians, what the great learning and vnderſtanding of the famous Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician <hi>Anthony Magino,</hi> Profeſſour of the Mathematickes, in <hi>Bononia</hi> in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> as alſo that hee hath particularly and generally made many Propheſies by the aſpects of the Planets, or courſe of the Heauens, and alſo ſhewed vnto mee many things, which now at this day I finde to be true, in reſpect of theſe reaſons, and many others the like. I was moued to ſet forth ſome of his Kalenders, which by his ſonne <hi>Fabians</hi> meanes came to my hands, with other things, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe ſhall come to light. This learned Aſtronomer, by reaſon of the diſeaſe of the Stone, was very ſickly, and many times as he was in his paſſion, he was deſired by ſome Cardinall, Duke, or Earle, that viſited him to ſet forth a Kalender or Propheſie, which ſometimes was very painefull vnto him, for theſe cauſes: he determined as ſoone as he was ſomewhat eaſed of his paine, to effect the ſame, and made a Kalender beginning at <hi>anno 1617.</hi> and continuing to <hi>anno 1630.</hi> which now foure yeares one after another hath beene Printed, and for the moſt part found to be true: for theſe cauſes I thought good to Tranſlate the ſame out of Italian, and to Print it in Dutch, and now into Engliſh.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4187:2"/>
            <head>BEFORE I BEGIN THIS Prognoſtication, I will let you ſee, <hi>what happened the laſt yeare.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome yeares paſt, there were the like Prognoſtications particularly ſet forth touching the former yeares, and that of the yeare 1622. now preſent, was entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Propheſier, made by <hi>Anthonius Maginus,</hi> ſometime a Mathematician, or Profeſſor ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Bononia</hi> in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> whoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was well knowne throughout the whole world, and ſhall yet be more knowne, for that all his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewings and Propheſies, are done by the Aſpects of the Planets, and the truth of things, although it be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying, Almanacks are a ſack full of lies, yet wee muſt not therefore contemne or deſpiſe the Art, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that ſometimes things may happen amiſſe: It is not ſo ſtrange a thing, for it daily happens ſo to our Countrey-men, when after the Sunne is ſet, we ſay wee ſhall haue faire weather, and it falleth out cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, both I my ſelfe and many more with me, know that the holy Scriptures ſpeake thereof: therefore theſe and the like reaſons, doe not make it a bad matter, the worke makes the Maſter to be commended, and if there be any man, whom in any ſort it doth concerne, let him looke it out in the book or Italian Propheſier, laſt yeare
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4187:3"/>
ſet forth, and conferre the ſame with the former times, and he ſhall finde according to humane wiſedome, that it was well done, and more then any other Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician of our time euer did. Before we come to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe, euery man muſt generally vnderſtand, that when he names ſuch an altitude, we muſt know, that the length from the Eaſt to the Weſt, is vncertainly taken, as in the yeare paſt, There was a great queſtion made, when he ſaid, out of the North to the South, vnder 44. 45. and 46. dayes, <hi>Mars</hi> the God of Warre will cauſe the red Cock to crowe: and that there ſhould be much innocent blood ſhed: whereby without doubt hee meant <hi>France,</hi> as in many places it may be ſhewed, and who was ſo wiſe, as to conceiue or once imagine, that there ſhould ſuch an alteration happen in that miſerable Countrey of <hi>France,</hi> ſpeaking alſo very certainly of the great Warre vpon the borders of the riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> and of <hi>Valtolina,</hi> as alſo of the altitude of <hi>Leefland,</hi> where the King of <hi>Swethland</hi> had great Warre againſt the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and brought the moſt part of that Countrey vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſubiection; and proceeding further, you ſhall finde that he ſpeakes of the white Eagle, and of them that beare the half Moon in their ſhield, of the heighths, where the great battailes were fought, betweene the Turke and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that beares the white Eagle, as the Emperour of <hi>Germanie</hi> beareth the blacke Eagle. Alſo touching the alteration in <hi>Hungariae,</hi> it is triple-wiſe ſet out, and of the blacke Sea, of the Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and other Countries there-abouts hee ſpeakes ſo exactly, as if hee had ſeene the ſame before. Whereof before that yeare there was no ſuſpition, he alſo ſpeakes of ſome wonders touching the heighth of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4187:3"/>
beares a chequer-boord in his Armes: he ſpeaketh fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and if wee looke neerely into the ſaid <hi>Maginoes</hi> writing: we ſhall finde wonderfull fore-ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thereof, but hee ſaith plainely, that his greatneſſe ſhall ſhrinke and faile, like a blaſt of winde before the fire, which as not now ſeemes not ſo. In the Countrey of <hi>Saxon,</hi> there are likewiſe great alterations fore-ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> moſt ſtrange things, which ſhall be eſteemed to be as fables; but time will cauſe it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare otherwiſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Warre in the Netherlands.</head>
               <p>TOuching the yeare paſt, what wagers were layd by diuers great perſonages, that thought they had the world at commaund, they made a full account a truce ſhould longer be made: but to the contrary, all his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſpeake of Warre, and that <hi>Mars</hi> the great man ſhould play his part, which ſufficiently appeares to be true. And further, if you looke narrowly into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, men may ſay that he was a Sayler, becauſe he ſpake much of preparation made by Sea, as well in the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean as the North Seas, and ſo forth. He hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fore-ſhewed much touching the Eaſt Indies, which hath fallen out to be true: for theſe and other reaſons I haue cauſed his Prognoſtication for <hi>anno</hi> 1622. to bee Printed, that all men might know the courſe of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prophecies">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4187:4"/>
            <head>Here begins the Italian Propheſier or Prognoſticator, practiſed by ANTONIO MAGINO, Profeſſour in the Vniuerſitie of the Citie <hi>Bononia</hi> in <hi>Lombardie.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IANVARIE.</head>
               <p>THE tenth of December old ſtile, the Sunne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into <hi>Capricornus,</hi> and then the Winter began, which was the 2. of December new ſtile, of the yeare paſt, being <hi>anno</hi> 1621. ſo that vpon the fourth of Ianuarie we haue the laſt quarter, and conſidering all the courſe of theſe Winter moneths, we finde that we ſhall haue a long cold froſty Winter, with much Haile and Snow, and that very thick vnder 52. degrees, but much fauourable windes: In high Countries there ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people die with cold and pouerty, they that die in Warre ſhall be free thereof.</p>
               <p>The 11. of Ianuarie, with the new Moone vnder the gouernment of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> there ſhall be many Rouers and murtherers ſeene, whereof men that trauell in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germanie,</hi> muſt beware: at that time alſo many wicked practiſes ſhall be inuented, and put in vre in <hi>Italy,</hi> to bring their neighbours on the hills vnto their ends.</p>
               <p>The 19. of Ianuarie the firſt quarter, many men ſhall ſpeake of peace, but <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> cannot agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the Sunne is entred into <hi>Aquarius,</hi> ſo that the matter is put to <hi>Neptune</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars.</hi> It ſhall be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4187:4"/>
to be in high degree, there ſhall alſo many bad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings come abroad, whereby men ſhall be in great feare of their liues, ſpecially vnder the height of 51. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ouer <hi>Britaine</hi> there will be a good Starre ſeene, as alſo ouer <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Sweathland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 27. of Ianuarie, the full Moone being in <hi>Leo,</hi> and the Sunne ſtill in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> ſignifies ſome ſtrange things to happen in the great Water-ſtreame, as alſo vpon the <hi>Rhine, Donaw, Elue</hi> in <hi>Stleſia, Liffeland, France</hi> and <hi>Grecia,</hi> in <hi>Sicilia</hi> in the Mediteranean Sea, there ſhall wonders be heard of, touching great burnings and blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; which <hi>Mars</hi> vpon the 30. of this moneth ſore threatneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FEBRVARIE 1622.</head>
               <p>THE 2. of Februarie ſhall be the laſt quarter, the Sunne ſtill in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> caſting great damps and miſts ouer <hi>Germanie,</hi> which will ſeeme as if they would darken the light of heauen, vnder the ſame to make ſome new aliances and contracts: many ſhall run away to ſhunne the wrath of God, but they ſhall be ouertaken by thoſe whom they leaſt ſuſpect, their goods ſhall be carried into ſtrange Countries.</p>
               <p>The 10. of Februarie, being new Moone, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> meete, to ſpeake of peace, that hath beene moued in <hi>Germanie,</hi> which will make much more alteration then was before, ſmall things ſhall be great.</p>
               <p>The 18. of Februarie, the firſt quarter, <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> were in <hi>Taurus,</hi> the Sunne in the laſt of <hi>Aquarius,</hi> figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with their beames one againſt the other, which are certaine tokens of ſome ſtrange matter, ſo that all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Chriſtians ought to pray vnto God, to beſeech
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4187:5"/>
him to withdraw his threatnings from vs.</p>
               <p>The 19. of Februarie, the Sunne in <hi>Piſces,</hi> with much vnwholſome cold South-weſt windes, contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>The 25. of Februarie, with the full Moone <hi>Saturne</hi> the child eater raigneth, with <hi>Venus</hi> a light woman, what good theſe two will procure, the next moneth enſuing will ſhew.</p>
               <p>Vpon the 27. of Februarie, the laſt aſpect of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets with <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> are in <hi>Libra,</hi> and more ſhall follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>MARCH.</head>
               <p>THE fourth of March, the laſt quarter, <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie</hi> raigne, the next day in the fourth aſpect <hi>Iupiter</hi> againe with <hi>Sol:</hi> This ſignifieth that many Kings and Princes ſhall meete together, to finde meanes to be quit of this Warre, becauſe their money conſumes, but <hi>Mars</hi> ſerues not to graunt thereunto, becauſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready he hath made a contract with <hi>Neptunes</hi> Fleet, to augment his Treaſure.</p>
               <p>The 12. of March, with the new Moone, many mens courages will faile, ſpecially vnder the heighth of 40. 41. 42. degrees, Northward of the line, others to the contrary ſhall be encouraged, that is vnder 51. 52. and 53. degrees: To ſend a great power to the Seas, the like whereof hath not been ſeene: as long as the world hath continued, they ſhall make the new world quake, and ſeeke to bind the Eaſt and the Weſt together; the Roſe and the Lilly ſhall ſet a root, although it be not ſeene.</p>
               <p>The 20. of March, the firſt quarter, the Sunne goeth out of <hi>Piſces,</hi> and leaues the land man in danger.</p>
               <p>The 21. of March, the Sunne entreth into <hi>Aries</hi> or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4187:5"/>
the Ram, &amp; paſſeth the Equinoctiall line: then day and night throughout all the world ſhall be of one length: and this Mathematician ſaith, that at that time all the Planets goe out of their houſes, onely <hi>Venus</hi> is in her houſe in <hi>Taurus,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> in her houſe in <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſo that they two are the Lords of this yeare, <hi>Mercurie</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnus</hi> their coadiutors; this matter being lookt into it, ſhall be found to be ſo.</p>
               <p>The 27. on Eaſter day, with the full Moone, there ſhall many variable windes blow, and it will be cold nights, in that time many ſhall luſtily make preparation for the Warres, not for the Hugonite nor the Papiſt, but for the Idoll money in the Cheſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>APRILL.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond of Aprill the laſt quarter, there ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hard cloudes with Hayle fall vpon the North Countries, and hee that hath good ſtore of Oates and Horſes before hand, ſhall make good profit of them: there will be bad payment, yet all kinde of Wares ſhall be well ſold, <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall conſume many, ſo that Husbandmen ſhall be forced to runne away with their Cattle and fowles.</p>
               <p>The 10. of Aprill a new Moone, the great King of Fowles ſhall beare fire in his breſt, therewith to hurt the Inhabitants in the Alpes, or in the heighth vnder the which the Switzers dwell: but in that time he muſt be warie, when he flies from his owne neſt, that his owne young ones be not hurt, and made ſlaues. The 6. aſpect with <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> are vpon the 11. day, yet in <hi>Aries</hi> vnder a ſheepes clothing, to diſcouer ſome ſecret thing.</p>
               <p>The 18. of Aprill the firſt quarter, the Moone was in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4187:6"/>
                  <hi>Leo,</hi> that ſignifies ſome ſtrange thing out of <hi>Turkie,</hi> and the adherents thereof againſt the Romane Empire, and the next day vpon the 19. the Sunne enters into <hi>Taurus:</hi> therefore all Countries vnder <hi>Taurus</hi> are to beware of themſelues, for they ſhall endure a great blow, ſuch as they ſhall hardly beare, they are ſore threatned by the aſpects of the Planets, ſpecially in the Weſt, therefore looke to the winde, it will blow.</p>
               <p>The 25. with the full Moone, <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> were in <hi>Libra,</hi> then a certaine number of <hi>Neptunes</hi> Wagons ſhall goe out of the Thames in <hi>England,</hi> to ſeek for the people vnder <hi>Taurus,</hi> with a great power, ſo that it ſeemes that all the Gods in the ayre gather together, onely to ſee the Sea Nimphes, but their weapons were fearefull: ſhortly after that, men ſhall heare a moſt pittifull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, like a womans vice, in the Weſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>MAY.</head>
               <p>THE 2. being in the laſt quarter, is the holy croſſe day, whoſe vertues are wonderfull, and many times haue done miracles: the other two dayes after Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion day, <hi>Saturne, Sol, Iupiter, Mercurie,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> ſhall be found in <hi>Aries,</hi> with diuers aſpects; whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that ſome great Prince ſhall vndergoe great danger.</p>
               <p>The 10. with a new Moone, <hi>Luna</hi> will be in the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons taile, which ſignifieth, that many turbulent ſpirits ſhall ſcatter abroad diuers ſlanderous Libels, in manner of merry ſongs, but Iuſtice will finde them out. In our Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> there ſhall be no Ecclipſe ſeene, but vpon the 10. day of May. In <hi>Africa,</hi> in the 20. degree of <hi>Taurus,</hi> there ſhall be a great Ecclipſe of the Sunne ſeene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4187:6"/>
there: Theſe ſignes auncient Aſtronomers haue eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be notable fore-ſhewings of ſome alreration.</p>
               <p>The 18. the firſt quarter, in the laſt Whitſon holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, there ſhall ſtrong windes blow in the North quarters; therefore Sea-faring men ſhall be fortunate that ſayle into South and Weſt.</p>
               <p>The 20. the Sunne ſhall enter into <hi>Geminie,</hi> ſo that thoſe that are wiſe, vnder that climate to begin any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, ſhall be fortunate therein, for their Enemies ſhall like children runne away in great feare, and giue them gold and ſiluer, which they ſhall carrie away for their wiues and children.</p>
               <p>The 24. the full Moone, preparation ſhall be made to enter into the field, that is in the North land, on the other ſide of the Alpes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IVNE.</head>
               <p>THE 2. of Iune the laſt quarter, it ſhall be faire plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant weather, and men ſhall ſeeke to lay ſwords and nets, to catch others in. There ſhall be blood-ſhedding in diuers places. The Turke ſhall fall vpon the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and driue them to an Vnity, as the Wolfe doth the Oxen: but ſome will not hearken thereunto, ſo that great trouble is to be expected, and if hee hath the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he ſhall enter farre into <hi>Europa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 9. a new Moone, a good courage ſhall bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to light, and if they hap well, it will be much furtherance for his adherents: and in this moneth, as long as the Sunne is in <hi>Geminie,</hi> the Subiects muſt be obedient to their Lords, or they will fall into great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, we ſhall heare ſtrange things out of <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 16. the firſt quarter, you ſhall haue ſome ſpeciall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4187:7"/>
matter out of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> in ſome things good for the Eaſt Countrie, and notable things out of <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 19. the Sunne is in <hi>Cancer,</hi> the firſt aſpect in <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> with many beames, ſo that it ſeemes, things will be turned topſie turuie, many men ſhall be beaten by <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 23. the full Moone, the Sunne enters into <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> which ſignifieth a great inuaſion in the Countries lying vnder <hi>Cancer,</hi> becauſe that two dayes before, ſome beames of the Planets ſhot that way, and alſo all the Planets at that time haue gathered together in the Sun, vnder the Twins, <hi>Leon</hi> and the Crab, <hi>Venus</hi> and Lucifer goe before, in that time, aboue our Netherlands Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, that is, in the morning before fiue of the clocke, vntill Iuly there ſhall a wonder be ſeene, which is not much ſeene, and ſhall without doubt produce a new fearefull commet, ere it be long: therefore turne vnto God, and pray that he will diuert his wrath from you.</p>
               <p>The 30. in the euening at 6. of the clock the laſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Moone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IVLY.</head>
               <p>THE 8. of Iuly the new Moone, you ſhall ſee all the 7. Planets aboue the Horriſon, as I ſaid before, you ſhall alſo heare of a new manner of Warre, which ſhall be raiſed by <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturnus,</hi> which ſhall ſend many home without armes and legs, but he that ſtayes there ſhall not be hang'd.</p>
               <p>The 14. the firſt quarter, you ſhall heare many ſtrange things out of <hi>Turkie</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> and alſo out of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Iſlands, in the way to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of <hi>France,</hi> you ſhall haue vnexpected things, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he furtherance of the North lands, people of meane
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4187:7"/>
quality ſhall waxe great, and ſpread their wings like a Pellican ouer her young ones, but before that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you ſhall heare wonders.</p>
               <p>The 20. the Sunne goes out of <hi>Cancer,</hi> and leaues her ſubiects in neceſſity, and that day enters into <hi>Leo,</hi> vnder whoſe gouernment all the Countries that beare the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their ſhield, ſhall be victorious. About <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> or in the Countries bordering about them, you ſhall heare of great battailes, that is vnder 46. or 47. degrees, looke in the Card, you ſhall eaſily ſee the places; about that time you ſhall alſo haue a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion vnder 50. degrees, which ſhall make many men flie out of the field from their bad enemies.</p>
               <p>The 22. with the full Moone, you ſhall alſo haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fires, and diuers hot diſeaſes, which ſhall kill and ſpoile many men.</p>
               <p>The 29. the firſt quarter, the Sunne in <hi>Leo,</hi> a great man ſhall be put to ſhame: and the common ſaying ſhall be true, that is, he that ſeekes to haue all, ſhall get nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>AVGVST.</head>
               <p>THE 7 being Sunday with the new Moone, you ſhal ſee the Sunne ſtill to be in <hi>Leo,</hi> and then ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Armies in the field, yea, as many as euer were ſeene in mans remembrance, much fruit ſhall be ſpoiled, the ſmall ſhall beat the great, and make his Subiects rich: therefore looke that you defend an vpright cauſe, and then you ſhall be participant therewith.</p>
               <p>The 13. the firſt quarter, many Forts and ſtrong holds aſſailed and vndermined, peſtilence and ſtrange ſicknes ſhall raigne; it ſhall be hot and dry weather, by reaſon that the ſaid Planets are very neere to the Sunne, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4187:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4187:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4187:9"/>
haue procured a great operation; alſo you ſhall haue great ſtore of Thunder with Earthquakes.</p>
               <p>The 19. the Sunne enters into <hi>Virgo,</hi> or the Mayde, there ſhall be faire and good fruit in ſome places, but not ſo much as the laſt yeare, but it ſhall be ripe in good time, that is, where it is not ſpoiled by the Enemy: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Virgo</hi> a motion ſhal againe be made touching peace, and it may poſſible be effected hereafter, by good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alledged.</p>
               <p>The 21. with the full Moone, he that protected and vpheld an vniuſt cauſe, ſhall be mock'd by all the world, and his adherents ſhall be ſorrowfull.</p>
               <p>The 29. the laſt quarter, you ſhall heare ſtrange things out of <hi>Barbarie,</hi> which before were little thought on, and the like out of <hi>Battauia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>SEPTEMBER.</head>
               <p>THE 5. of September, with the new Moone, you ſhall ſee he that climes high ſhall be brought low, a ſtrange Cock ſhall crowe there: there ſhall be great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and pouerty in the hilly Countries, there ſhall be great peſtilence and dearth: therefore watch and pray, for who knowes whom GOD will puniſh with theſe plagues.</p>
               <p>The 12. the firſt quarter, you ſhall ſee great ſmokes in the ayre with the burning of ſome ſtuffe, as in times paſt men vſe to make Boon-fires for ioyes of victorie, and there ſhall many be crowned with Lawrell, for the former victories; to the contrary others ſhall be clad in mourning weedes, to weepe for, and to bury their dead.</p>
               <p>The 19. the full Moone, before the Sunne goes out of <hi>Virgo,</hi> we ſhall heare of the aſſembling of many Prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4187:9"/>
to treate of waighty matters, as the Planets ſufficiently giue vs to vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>The 20. the Sunne in <hi>Libra,</hi> ſignifieth high water, and low Countries ſhall ſuffer great danger, much no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table alteration ſhall be in diuers places, all good for Sea-faring men, that trauaile in ſtrange Countries.</p>
               <p>The 23. Harueſt ſhall begin, and it ſhall be warme and dry, in reſpect of the reaſons afore-ſaid, the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fruit ſhall be good.</p>
               <p>The 27. the laſt quarter, they that haue vſed falſe waight, ſhall vndergoe great danger, whereby there will be ill earnings, and bad payments, and may bankerupts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>OCTOBER.</head>
               <p>THE 4. of October, the new Moone, you ſhall ſee many Ships vpon the water, ſeruing for the War, there ſhall be no want of booty nor blowes: The inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſhall endure much wrong, by burnings and other barbarian tyrannies, neuer heard of, extortions, and abuſing of women and children.</p>
               <p>The 11. the firſt quarter, there ſhall be much good Wine found in many places, much better then the laſt yeare, but the owners thereof ſhall not enioy them all.</p>
               <p>The 19. the full Moone, the Sunne goes out of <hi>Libra,</hi> ſome Princes ſhall ſeeke ſo to mittigate matters, that they may be quit of the afore-ſaid Warres, and thereby liue peaceably againe.</p>
               <p>The 20. the Sunne in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> a very bad ſigne for wounded men, ſpecially for the Spaniards and Italians, for that cold will ſtrike into their wounds, and vnder <hi>Scorpio</hi> make them die: therefore in that time be gone, as faſt as you can.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4187:10"/>The 27. the laſt quarter, there ſhall come many bad tydings, but it will ſoone be cold, therefore you <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uians</hi> be watchfull, ſtrike with an Angels minde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, for then it begins to be ſlaughter time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>NOVEMBER.</head>
               <p>THE 3. of Nouember, the full Moone, <hi>Luna</hi> will be in the Dragons head, ſo that ſome vnder the height of 50. degrees, that haue Miters on their heads, ſhall fall into great neceſſity, after that their Countrey is ſpoyled and burnt, and their Subiects deſtroyed, who then ſhall call for peace, but ſhall not be heard: theſe men afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Magino,</hi> thinkes that they are <hi>Ments, Tryer,</hi> and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> or ſome Countries bordering vpon them.</p>
               <p>The 3. of Nouember, you ſhall haue an Ecclipſe of the Sunne, which ſhall not be ſeene in <hi>Europa,</hi> but ouer the Indian lands: yet they of <hi>Europa</hi> muſt not therefore thinke, that they ſhall not be participant with his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe, but muſt know that the force thereof extendeth ouer the whole world.</p>
               <p>The 10. the firſt quarter, vnder 50 ½. degrees, ouer <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Zealand,</hi> you ſhall heare good newes out of ſtrange Countries, and many ſtrange things, but they muſt be very wary, there will variable windes blow, and high floods riſe.</p>
               <p>The 18. the full Moone, the Sunne will ſtill be in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and in that time much misfortune ſhall happen, in thoſe Countries where Scorpions are to be found, that is, in <hi>Italy, Spaine, Barbarie,</hi> and in <hi>India,</hi> and alſo hurtfull for the ſame Nations, in what Countrey ſoeuer they ſhall be, by reaſon of the aſpects afore-ſaid.</p>
               <p>The 21. the Sunne enters into <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> vnder his gouernment there ſhall be great preparation of Warre,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4187:10"/>
by <hi>Neptunes</hi> Fleet out of the North, to be made in the South, more then in long time hath been ſeene, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together vnder 36. and 37. degrees, in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diteranean Sea.</p>
               <p>The 26. the laſt quarter, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Neptune,</hi> bids many to geſt with Powder and Match, there ſhall be a great battaile by water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DECEMBER.</head>
               <p>THE 2. of December, the new Moone, Warre in the North lands ſhall leſſen, and encreaſe South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: there ſhall alſo great ſtore of Ordnance be made ready, and preparation of great Ships made, to aſſaile ſtrange Countries.</p>
               <p>The 9. the firſt quarter, many cold windes ſhall blow, high floods, ſignifying a colde Winter, with many ſtormes of Hayle.</p>
               <p>The 17. a full Moone, there ſhall many things bee practiſed, and there ſhal be many Ambaſſadors ſent, to treate of peace: ſome Princes will ſit downe, when they ſee that <hi>Sagitarius</hi> hath his bowe ſtill bent, to threaten them with great loſſe of their riches and blood.</p>
               <p>The 21. on Wedneſday, the Sunne entreth into the hard headed <hi>Capricornus,</hi> much addicted to butting, but it ſhall happen vnder his climate: There ſhall be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull tydings heard of, and much complaint, out of <hi>Germany, Italy, Poland,</hi> and other farre Countries.</p>
               <p>The 25. the laſt quarter, being Chriſtmas day, many ſhall die with cold, becauſe that in the Summers paſt they could get nothing, by reaſon of the former Wars. Therefore pray vnto God, that hee by his great power, will make the yeare enſuing better, whereby his name ſhall be praiſed, now and for euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="complaints">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4187:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Complaints made by diuers Nations touching their preſent ſtate.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spaniard ſpeakes.</head>
               <p>WHo is like vnto me, in all the world, euen from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt, it is but chaffe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of fine gold of <hi>Peru:</hi> behold our power out of our Countrey, which is <hi>Naples, Millaen, Sicilia, Corſica, Sardinia,</hi> and <hi>Malta,</hi> and the foot that wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently haue in the <hi>Griſons</hi> and <hi>Switzerland:</hi> the higher and lower <hi>Palatinate,</hi> with <hi>Gulick, Cleaue,</hi> and <hi>Berghe:</hi> alſo our hereditarie Countries of the Netherlands, with the notable aliance of the ſpirituality, and the confederates in marriage, as <hi>Auſtria, Sauoy,</hi> and the other ſtand vpon good termes, who hath ſo many gold Mines and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes as our King: firſt in <hi>Ginnea,</hi> and in all the <hi>Indies,</hi> where gold, ſiluer, and precious ſtones are to be found, as well in the Kingdomes of <hi>Goa, Sumatra, Borneo, Selebes, Banda;</hi> the vnſpeakeable Ilands of <hi>Molucka, Philippinaes, Manilles,</hi> and <hi>Iapan,</hi> with all the golden Kingdomes of the new world, as <hi>Chilla, Peru, Granada, Iucatan, Noua Hiſpania,</hi> and new <hi>Mexico:</hi> all the notable Ilands of <hi>Cuba, Hiſpaniola, Iaymaca,</hi> and <hi>Santo Croys,</hi> and thouſands there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, we rule ouer <hi>Braſillia,</hi> and the ſiluer ſtreame, of the <hi>Amaſons, Rio Grande, Rio de Plato,</hi> to the Straights of <hi>Magelanus,</hi> with the Canaries and the Flemiſh Ilands, who dares be ſo bold as to lift vp his head againſt vs, or point to vs in <hi>Spaine,</hi> to bid vs milke our Aſſes, make Fig Frayles, and ſuch like things, all of vs are Knights, and all is ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:4187:11"/>
               <head>The Italian.</head>
               <p>THis pride is not to be borne withall, that we ſhould in this manner ſuffer the manly members &amp; bodies of our Neapolitanes, Sicilians, Corcicaners, and Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinians, to be ſo much bridled, ſpecially we that are Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, whoſe might and dominion cauſed the whole world to ſhake for feare, and now by a few Lucitaneans, or bragging Spaniards, to be out-faced: it is too much, <hi>Tuſcania, Florence, Lombardy, Millaen, Parma,</hi> and <hi>Mantua,</hi> with the two famous Common-wealthes of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Genua,</hi> I ſpeake not of <hi>Treuiſano, Ferara,</hi> and <hi>Verona,</hi> haue thus long beene bewitcht, to ſuffer theſe bloody Culli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which haue not beene knowne aboue 150. yeares paſt, in ſuch manner to encroach vpon our dominions, vnder pretence of we know not what, I am in doubt it will be our ouerthrow.</p>
               <p>If we driue them not out of our borders, for I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that it will come to the ſame paſſe that wee were brought vnto by the Gothes and Vandales, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded ouer our Countrey 300. yeares together, and ſpoyled the ſame, as by the ruines thereof left; it is yet to be ſeene, we are not to expect any better then this from the Turke, and that with good reaſon, becauſe the Spaniard, not long ſince prepared and made ready his ſhips in our Hauens, and did ſome exploits in the Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Ilands, belonging to the Turke. Therefore let vs vnite our ſelues together, &amp; force the Spaniard to leaue our borders, our Countrey is ſtrong enough to defend it ſelfe, we are encloſed round about by the Sea, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> we haue the Alpes, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue beene our good neighbours, that is, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyans, Switzers, and Griſons, whom they now fight
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4187:12"/>
withall as Enemies, they ſay that they are hereticks, and vnder pretence thereof, would pull the ſtoole from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs: whereunto ſome of our Countrey men are aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: therefore riſe vp, for it is more then time, make you ready for the Warre, and to ſpeake the truth, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beleeue that there is any of our Nation to be found, that would ſuffer himſelfe to be hang'd or burnt for the confeſſion of the faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Turke.</head>
               <p>WE ſweare by our God, and <hi>Mahomet</hi> our great Prophet, that we will not endure the wrong that not long ſince hath been done vnto vs in <hi>Grecia</hi> and elſe where, by certaine Spaniſh ſhips, that were prepared and made ready in <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſweare as afore, that before the ſiluer Moone, ſhall haue ſhewed her face with cleare light ſeauen times: we will teach them to know who is Emperour, though we ſhould make peace with <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> and therewith employ our power, of <hi>Podolia, Meldauia, Walachta, Bulgaria, Seruia,</hi> and all <hi>Grecia,</hi> with all the Ilands thereof, <hi>Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lia,</hi> or <hi>Aſia:</hi> The borders of the blacke Salt, and Mediteranian Seas: I ſpeake not of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Iudea, Egipt,</hi> and <hi>Barbaria,</hi> and all the reſt belonging to the Turkiſh power, wee will ſet vpon and aſſaile all you that are truce breakers, and vtterly root you out, to the laſt man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Polander.</head>
               <p>ALas, what doth it auaile vs, that we haue giuen ayde to the Emperour or the Spaniard, whereby wee haue beene forced to ſuſtaine three cruell Warres, that is, with the Swethlanders, Muſcouites, and the great Turke, who ſpoyleth all our land, and if we cannot ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily make peace with the Turk, all our Country will be ſpoyled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4187:12"/>
               <head>The Hungarian.</head>
               <p>VVE that are Souldiers, and men of courage, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues in all occurrents that happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, vnleſſe it be, when men ſeeke to bring a ſtrange Nation of Spaniards to domineere ouer vs, threatning to deale with vs, as they did in <hi>India,</hi> with the Country people there: but that is not yet brought to paſſe, haue we withſtood ſo great a Warre, as all men know: wee will rather with our owne Nation, in ſteed of ſuffering our King, to draw backe and giue way, ſeeke to enlarge our borders, as farre as we finde any Spaniards to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand vs, and wil ſet vpon them all as Enemies, and make a prey of their lands and goods, and will rather burne vp our owne houſes, and eate our horſes fleſh, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Subiects vnto the Spaniards or the Auſtrians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Germanes.</head>
               <p>VVHat bad and crafty dealing is this, There comes a hundred thouſand diuels, with that blacke company, that are brought into the land by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, be it as it will be, Hayle and Thunder conſume them all, both Spirituall and Temporall: It is no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for vs Germanes, to ſeeke to preuaile by ſuch a company of Raſcalls, Pots excrement: a ſhame take all the villanous Prieſts men, and their Wallon ſlaues, was, was, was: cannot we that are Germanes luſtily fall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the eares, and fight, and then againe drinke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and be friends. Was, was, it is to great ſhame: There is no remedy, but that wee Germanes generally altogether muſt driue the Spaniards out of the land, or elſe we ſhal liue vnder their yoake all our liues long, and euer haue Warre in our Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4187:13"/>
               <head>The French-man.</head>
               <p>ONe deuill or other heere in our Countrey, hath thruſt his ſticke into the wheele, ſeeing that many yeeres together we haue with great vnity tollerated the Religion, and now by meanes of a Spaniſh Ieſuite, this heauie and deadly trouble is raiſed, whereby many men come to their ends. If all that vngodly company of Spaniſh brood were in <hi>India,</hi> wee might be in hope of a peace. It ſeemes that whereſoeuer the Spaniard comes, Gods bleſſing is baniſhed farre from thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Switzers and Griſons.</head>
               <p>VVHat haue we done? whoſe Countrey haue wee taken from them? or what riches are here to be found? but onely true Chriſtian blood: God haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon vs; for the great and miſerable complaints of women and children are exceeding much, they neither ſpare Catholike nor thoſe of the Religion, in this great extremity: it is vnſpeakeable, what barbarous cruelty is at this day vſed here vpon poore oppreſſed men, by murthering, fleaing, ſlitting their noſes, diſmembring their bodies ioynt from ioynt, caſting them downe from the tops of hills into the water, ripping of womens bodies, to ſee the place from whence men come forth; and with a thouſand the like vnſpeakeable manners of torments and deathes, to kill and deſtroy the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of our Countries, and to driue the reſt away, and make the remainer become obedient vnto them: take example by vs, not to truſt the Spaniards nor his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but kill, before you are killed, and ſo you ſhall haue peace, and doe well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4187:13"/>
               <head>The Engliſh man, Dane, Swetherlander, and Netherlander.</head>
               <p>VVEE haue taught this Tyrant partly to know himſelfe, and therefore wee gnaſh our teeth at him, and purpoſe rather with weapons in our hands, to die then to liue vnder ſuch a Tyrant, or to endure his intollerable yoake: and without doubt, if any of theſe Nations loue the Spaniard, then for certaine they are of his minde, or at leaſt ſome of his conquered Baſtards, which hee ouercame in the time, that hee was in theſe Countries, and vnleſſe it be the Woolfe, I know no beaſt, that willingly will ſuffer another beaſt to lye in his neſt or denne, vnleſſe it be a Cucko: we finde ſome in theſe Countries, that put their children to Schoole to learne Spaniſh, in that language to yeeld all honour and curteſie vnto thoſe Signieurs, thereby to make him beleeue, that that honour iuſtly belongs vnto him, to rule and domineere ouer all Nations, whereof hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth himſelfe to be worthy, and to deſerue it. No, no, not ſo, but keepe the Hollanders, Swethlanders, and Freſeland, from yeelding thereunto, and who ſo euer ſo withſtands the Spaniard, it ſhall goe well with him, and they ſhall leaue their children great riches in this world, and in the world to come euerlaſting life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:4187:14"/>
               <head>The Indians.</head>
               <p>VVE poore Indians can neither write nor reade, and as yet haue not ſeene many more Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but the Spaniards: but none of our Nation wiſh to enter into that heauen, where the Spaniards ſaid they ſhall goe, but rather to leape into the burning hill of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> and to ſtay there: they haue moſt barbarouſly murthered and ſlaine all our Kings and Princes, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away all their goods, and put many thouſands of our Indians, by the greateſt torments that can be inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to miſerable deathes, which ſtill is in our mindes: and if once the great Creator that rules the Sunne and Moone, would releaſe vs out of this tyrannie, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ioy could there be heard of in <hi>India,</hi> and wee hope that ere it be long, it will come to paſſe, for our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets haue fore-ſhewed the ſame. Signieur, what think you: Is it not time with all ſpeede to ſmeare your ſelfe with Hares greace? Yes, yes, yes. <hi>Vamos.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4187:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
